Finding aid for Charles W. Lane papers, 1935-1997 9840 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library
Charles W. Lane papers
1935-1997
1958-1969
Bentley Historical Library
Lane, Charles W. (Charles Wesley), 1919-
9840 Aa 2
4.5 linear feet in 6 boxes
7 oversize folders
Architect based in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Project files relate to work with George Brigham and his system of constructing prefabricated homes, 1944-1947; files relating to design and construction of Huron High School in Ann Arbor; other projects concern design of mobile home parks and other Michigan school buildings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Charles Wesley Lane (donor 8716 ) in 1998; additions were received from the family in 2008.
Accruals
No further additions to the papers are expected.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to research, except for some files in box 2 that are restricted to staff use only.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Wesley Lane was born in 1919. He began his career as an architect by working at construction sites during his summer breaks from the University of Michigan, from 1937 through 1941. He then worked for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers on the MacArthur Lock in Sault St. Marie. Following Lane's graduation from the University of Michigan he served in World War II. He was in Louisiana for a short time, helping to supervise construction of a blimp hangar. He then began work as a Photo Interpretation officer and was part of the landing at Iwo Jima and Okinawa. He also spent some time in Nagasaki after the atomic bomb. Upon returning he went to work as an architect for George Brigham in Ann Arbor. Brigham's office was divided into two areas, research and production. Lane was assigned to work in research as an architect for Brigham's Progressive Homes Corporation (PHC). The goal of PHC was to design a completely prefabricated home that could be erected in eight hours (with the footings already in place) for the price of $1500. Brigham began the company with funders that included Eugene Cassaroll of Dual Motors. Lane describes the other investors as "auto people from Detroit." The investors disassociated Brigham from the research division when his pace of development did not move along as quickly as they had hoped. The head of PHC was Ira E. "Mickey" Gillen, a former production manager for Chrysler Motors.
Gillen and the investors acquired 100,000 square feet of space in Pine Bluff, Arkansas to manufacture their homes. Gillen arranged for the building supplies to come from a variety of companies across the U.S. In a reflection of Gillen's automotive background, he wanted the pieces of the houses brought to Arkansas and assembled as pieces of a car are brought to a central location to be assembled. Gillen set up dealerships for the houses in every state and in England, France and South America. In South America he had a contract for 10,000 homes and in California a naval station wanted 5,000 houses, if they were financed by the Federal Housing Administration. The first two manufactured homes were built in Indiana, then Wisconsin. At about the fifth or sixth house, the local authorities would not issue a building permit because the local plumbers union was against the use of stamped steel in the building. Gillen had the support of the Federal Housing Administration (FHA) over the plumbers, but the FHA still would not finance the homes. This was the end of the company because no one would finance the building of the houses. Since 1947, 400 homes had come off of the assembly line. Those homes were built around Washington D.C. because of a contract the PHC had with the government, which the latter was forced to honor. By 1948, about 250 similar companies producing manufactured homes had sprung up around the United States.
After the failure of PHC, Lane went to work for the Walter Aneche firm in Ann Arbor; he worked at the firm from 1948 to 1952. Lane designed drawings for Good Housekeeping and schools in Michigan. In 1952 Lane established his own firm in Ann Arbor with architects Alex Riebe and Keith Weiland. Lane developed a 24 x 36 steel sheet that was repetitive and was used in about 400 schools in Michigan. Lane designed many schools and residences throughout Michigan with his firm. The firm was hired in the 1960s to design Huron High School in Ann Arbor, Michigan. This was the largest, most unique school that he designed. He originally made 17 designs of the building, all which were rectangular in shape. In an effort to save money he created a circular design that reduced corridor space and cost. Lane was lauded for the unique design and budget reducing measures. In addition to the actual structure, Lane also made recommendations, which were followed, on where Huron Parkway should be placed.
In 1971, shortly after the completion of Huron High School, Lane left his firm to pursue his interest in manufactured housing. Alex Riebe moved the firm to Farmington, Michigan. Lane saw that many of the same obstacles remained, with the exception of the invention of the mobile home park. In the late 1960s Lane designed a mobile home park in Almont, Michigan which was unique because it had paved streets, parking, and landscaping.
Scope and Contents
The collection is arranged into five series, Brigham Building System, Lane Projects, Huron High School, Personal and World War II Military Service. The series include the many projects that Charles Wesley Lane worked on during his architectural career and some materials from his military service as well. The collection is composed of photographs, slides, microfilm, microfiche and prints. The researcher will be interested in the variety of architectural projects in which Lane was involved, which include schools, mobile homes, churches, and other types of structures. A small number of photographs of Nagasaki after the atomic bomb may also be of interest.
Architectural practice -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Architects -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Buildings, Prefabricated.; Mobile home parks -- Michigan.; Schools -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; World War, 1939-1945.; Architectural drawings.; Hawaii.; Houma (La.); Iwo Jima, Battle of, Japan, 1945.; Iwo Jima (Volcano Islands, Japan); Manila (Philippines); Nagasaki-Shi (Japan) -- History -- Bombardment, 1945.; Okinawa Island (Japan); Wakayama-Shi (Japan) -- History -- Bombardment, 1945.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Japan -- Okinawa Island.; Military art and science.; Mobile homes.; Schools -- Michigan.; Schools -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; War damage -- Japan -- Iwo Jima (Volcano Islands); War damage -- Japan -- Nagasaki-Shi.; War damage -- Japan -- Okinawa Island.; War damage -- Japan -- Wakayama-Shi.; War damage -- Philippines -- Manila.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Destruction and pillage.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military personnel.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military life.; Architectural drawings.; Photographs.; Lane, Charles W. (Charles Wesley), 1919-; Brigham, George Bickford, 1889-; Huron High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Lane, Charles W. (Charles Wesley), 1919-; Huron High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
- Brigham Building Systems
  Scope and Contents
  The first series Brigham Building System (1944-1947, 1997) consists of prints, research designs and slides that document the process that Charles Lane went through to produce some of the first manufactured homes. The researcher should take special interest in the stress tests that were performed on the building materials at the University of Michigan, with the help of Professor George McConkey. Also of interest are the prints of the several models that Lane proposed.
  - Project Files
    - Bill of Materials, Model 466-A, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Brigham Residence, Ann Arbor, Clipping, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Cutting Bills, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Design Analysis of Panels, circa 1947 (Box 1)
    - Progressive Homes
      - Drawings, 1947; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Erection Manual, circa 1947 (Box 1)
      - General, circa 1947 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Slides, Pine Bluff AK, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Test Report, 1947; 2 folders (Box 1)
      General
      photos enclosed in first folder
  - Architectural prints, etc.
    - Prints of Brigham Building System Models, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Lane Projects
  Lane Projects (1948-1983), the second series, documents the various types of projects, like residences and schools, that Lane spent the majority of his career designing. The researcher should note that in the first subseries - "General" - are two brochures. The brochures show photos, and list many of the projects that Lane's firm designed before 1966. Within this series are several roles of negative microfilm.
  - General Information
    - Master Contracts (Box 5)
    - Brochure No 1, Lane, Riebe, and Weiland Architects, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Brochure No 2, Lane, Riebe, and Weiland Architects, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Brochure for Charles W. Lane Associates, Inc., undated (Box 1)
    - Lists of Projects, as of, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Various Examples, undated (Box 1)
  - Project Files
    - Almont Ordinance No 61, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Faust Dental Clinic, Ann Arbor, MI with photos, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Kapok Travel Trailer Park, Clearwater, FL, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Manufactured Housing, slides
      - 1968 (Box 1)
    - Mobile Home Manufactures Association with slides
      - 1967 (Box 1)
      - 1968 (Box 1)
    - New Concepts in Low Cost Housing from Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, 1967 (Box 1)
    - New Housing System Concepts, Mobile Home Manufacturers Association, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Northlane Mobile Home Park and Center Building (photos enclosed), 1971 (Box 1)
    - Northlane Mobile Home Park
      - Clippings, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Photos (Box 5)
      - Reduced tracings of master plan (Box 5)
      - Slides, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Residences
      see also oversize drawer
      - Slides, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Schools
    - American School of the International Schools of the Hague
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - Design Program, 1972 (Box 1)
      - Drawings, 1972 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (photos enclosed), 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Almont Elementary School, (photo and slides), 1949; 1953 (Box 1)
    - Cadillac School Survey, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Franklin High School, Livonia, MI educational specifications, 1960; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Freeland Senior High School educational specifications, 1959 (Box 1)
      see also microfilm in box 2
    - Holly Area Schools, space needs report, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Lakewood Elementary School, Ann Arbor, MI, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Lewis L. Forsythe Junior High School, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Ontonagon School Study, University of Michigan Bureau of School Services, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Orchard Hills Elementary School, Novi, MI photo, 1958 (Box 1)
    - St. Mary's Lake Conference, "How to Plan Better Secondary Schools,", 1957 (Box 1)
    - School District List, Staff and Board of Education Members, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Stevenson High School, Livonia MI educational specifications, 1965 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Biological Station at Douglas Lake photo, 1983 (Box 1)
      see also prints in oversize drawer, folder 4
    - Miscellaneous Schools
      - Clippings, 1960-1967 (Box 1)
      - Microfiche and photos, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - Photos, circa 1950-1970 (Box 1)
      - Slides, 1948-1964 (Box 1)
      - Photos (Box 5)
  - Microfilm of miscellaneous projects, 13 film reels master negative only
    - Bates and Wylie Schools, Dexter, MI
      - Additions, Specifications and Addenda, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Educational Equipment for Additions, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Lakewood Elementary School, Ann Arbor, MI: plans, specifications and addenda, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Community Evangelical United Brethren Church, Ypsilanti, MI, 1967 (Box 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted; staff only
    - Lincoln and Jefferson Elementary School, Wayne, MI: additions, plans and specifications, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Livonia, MI, Section 31 Elementary School: Plans and Specifications, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Municipal Airport, Ann Arbor, MI: Service Hanger Plans and Specifications, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Novi Elementary School, Novi, MI: Remodeling Plans and Specifications, 1968 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan North Campus Development Inter-Council, 1969 (Box 2)
- Huron High School
  see also oversize drawer, folders 5-7 and microfilm in box 2
  The third series, Huron High School (1964-1997) contains materials that were used in the building of Huron High School, Ann Arbor, Michigan. These materials include what Lane referred to as "production books" which document the day-to-day progress of construction, prints of architectural drawings and educational specifications guides in which the staff of the future high school specified what their needs would be in the new building. The unique circular design of the school required that Lane draw his original designs on Mylar so that the circular pattern would be completely accurate; the use of Mylar at that time was seen as a novelty. This series contains articles that were written about the high school and published in a variety of magazines.
  - Ann Arbor by Windsor Publications, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Architectural Forum, advertisement for Republic Steel Lockers, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Binders on progress, 4 folders
    - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 3)
  - Circular Physical Education Complex, Use of Tectum Form Plank, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Construction Report, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Data Sheet and Educational Specifications Summary, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Dead File, circa 1964; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Educational Specifications
    - 1964-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
  - Exhibition Model and Display Boards for National School Board Conference and Exhibit, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Harris, Judy. CAM magazine freelance writer (Box 4)
  - Journal of American Concrete Institute, article about A.Z. Schmina (Box 4)
  - Nations Schools Report on Award Winning Schools, 1967 (Box 4)
  - "6.7 Million for New Swimming Pool," clipping, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Tectum Trends article, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Celebration, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Photos, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Personal
  The Personal series includes material documenting Lane's education and early employment. A small number of photographs of Lane are also included.
  - Clippings
    - Almont, Michigan (Box 6)
    - Atomic Bomb (Box 6)
    - Iwo Jima (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Education and Employment Record, 1935-1948 (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Charles Wesley (Wes) Lane (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Scholarship to Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1941 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan Senior Thesis, 1941-1942 (Box 6)
- World War II Military Service
  The last series, World War II Military Service, includes scrapbooks and photographs from Lane's service in the U.S. Navy. One scrapbook is dedicated to Lane's service in Louisiana and another documents a period of leave in Hawaii. There are also photographs of various events and locations in Japan. The landings and occupation of Iwo Jima and Okinawa are depicted. Also, there a small number of photographs showing the destruction in Nagasaki after the dropping of the atom bomb.
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
  - General (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Fuji Yama (Mt. Fuji), Japan, undated (Box 6)
    - Houma, Louisiana, 1943 (Box 6)
    - Iwo Jima, Japan, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Manila, Philippines, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Nagasaki, Japan (includes atomic bomb damage), 1945 (Box 6)
    - Okinawa, Japan, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Sasebo, Japan, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Various Locations, Japan, 1945; undated (Box 6)
    - Wakayama, Japan, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Unidentified (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Hawaii, 1944 (Box 6)
    - Louisiana, 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)